Calum Hand PhD.

calumhand201@gmail.com | (+44) 07765771639 | https://www.linkedin.com/in/calum-hand/ | Bristol, UK

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

A highly motivated machine learning engineer with 3+ years experience in developing, and productionising end-to-end AutoML pipelines in drug discovery with a further 4+ years in chemistry based AI research. Led courses related to software engineering for fellow students during my PhD. A subject matter expert across a range of green and renewable technologies and their intersection with AI; always looking forwards to expand my knowledge to learn about new fields and applications of the scientific process.

SKILLS

- o Technologies: Python, SQL, Metaflow, AWS, Git, Bash, SQLAlchemy, Poetry, Anaconda
- o Libraries: Pytest, Scikit-learn, Pytorch, Optuna, DuckDB, Pyarrow, Pandas, Numpy, Numba, Cuda, MlFlow, GPFlow, RDKit
- o DevOps: Docker, CodeBuild, CodeDeploy, Github Actions

EXPERIENCE

Machine Learning Engineer

Remote, UK

Glamorous AI: An X-CHEM Subsidiary

May 2022 - Current

An AutoMl SaaS platform allowing drug discovery teams to train state-of-the-art AI models on their data to reduce time and costs associated with conventional screening. A wide range of different models and featurisations are screened and optimised to achieve the best performing model for the client's data.

• Key Responsibilities:

- Productionizing AI models and tooling specialised for chemistry to run at scale
- Maintaining AI prediction pipelines, internal data lakehouse, and associated APIs
- Following TDD, striving for 90% test coverage in all projects worked on
- Instigating and organising a weekly meetup for the researchers to present problems and findings
- Conducting research and benchmarking into new AI methodologies for the drug discovery process
- Acting as scrum master in fortnightly agile development sprints
- Conducting live demonstrations for clients as an SME during product onboarding sessions

Datastore

- Independently planned and implemented the entire private data lakehouse to reduce computation times during AI training and inference by taking user input and transforming into persisted features for ML models (Python, DuckDB, SQL, Pyarrow, SQLAlchemy, S3, RDS)
- Designed the datastore to be a user friendly client library and tool, ensuring full adoption across research and engineering teams
- Reduced prediction pipeline run times by half

• Molecular Docking Simulation Pipeline:

- Lead the design and productionization of a molecular docking simualtion pipeline to pre-filter large molecular databases for high throughput drug candidate screenings (Python, Docker, Metaflow, Argo, Poetry, Pytest, SQLAlchemy)
- Completed pipeline could process hundreds of thousands molecules in under 2 hours while minimising costs through considered compute instance collection

• Similarity Screening Pipeline:

- Designed and Implemented a large scale pipeline using EKS cluster for a molecular fingerprint similarity calculation achieving 2.5 billion similarity calculations in 10 minutes (Python, Docker, Metaflow, Pyarrow, Poetry, Pytest)

• Domain Applicability:

- Led the research, development and optimisation of several unsupervised approaches to identify when the domain of the trained model doesn't match the domain of the prediction dataset (Python, Scikit-learn, Poetry, Pytest, Numpy, Optuna)
- Research was conducted on internal chemical datasets resulting in correctly identifying 66% of benchmark AI model prediction errors

Machine Learning Engineer Intern

Remote, UK

Glamorous AI : An X-CHEM Subsidiary

Oct 2021 - April 2022

- Conducted market analysis to identifying three further market areas for potential expansion with findings presented to stakeholders
- Implemented several python packages to aid researchers in the drug discovery process including: visualisation of chemical library overlap; unified data retrieval pipelines from multiple public data sources; and a wide collection of metrics for molecular similarity (Python, Docker, github actions, Conda, Scikit-learn, Pandas, Dask, Numpy, Rdkit, Requests)

- Researched various state of the art multi-input deep neural networks for predicting molecule binding affinity in different protein targets
- o Presented summary of literature review, model analysis, and benchmark results to stakeholders
- Identified and implemented the best model based on predictive performance and viability of implementation (Python, Pytorch, AWS, Docker, Conda)

IKEEP Collaborator Bath, UK

Co-Forest Ltd

- Worked as part of three person intrapreneurial knowledge exchange program between local business and PhD researchers
- o Project involved creating a plan to establish sense of community within Co-forest public and industrial clients
- The outcomes of this collaboration included the identification of company goals in order to create content for specific customers and the drafting of relevant promotional materials.

Account Team Member London, UK

RIMES Technologies (Financial Data Management)

Aug 2017 - Aug 2018

Feb 2021

- Was responsible for maintaining clients data feeds, including the investigation and analysis of any data discrepancies and errors raised in within RIMES in house coding language
- Rapidly promoted within six months to work with RIMES largest client, acting as subject matter expert and advising the client on the development of their new data feeds

Climbing Tower Staff & Counsellor

Virginia, USA

YMCA Camp Silver Beach

May 2015 - Aug 2015

- Worked as staff for the rock climbing tower and counsellor to cabin of 13 campers
- Expected to be autonomous in our day to day work caring for over 120 campers a week

EDUCATION

PhD in Chemical Engineering

Bath, UK

University of Bath

Oct 2019 - March 2023

Developed methodologies for Bayesian optimisation based active learning for reduced cost high throughput screenings

MRes Sustainable Chemical Technologies

Bath, UK

University of Bath

Sept 2018 - Sept 2019

Researched Active learning in material screenings, and novel vaccination preparations to mitigate cold chain risks

MRes Green Chemistry London, UK

Imperial College London

Sept 2016 - Sept 2017

Developed novel synthetic routes to sustainable furan monomer units for organic based solar cells

BSc Chemistry with Medicinal Chemistry

St. Andrews, UK

University of St. Andrews

Sept 2012 - June 2016

Developed a novel synthetic route valorising ligning as a biorenewable source of aromatic carbon

PUBLICATIONS

- "Autonomous Exploration and Identification of High Performing Adsorbents using Active Learning" : ChemRxiv: 10.26434/ChemRxiv:14555706.V1
- "Bayesian Screening: Multi-test Bayesian Optimization Applied to in silico Material Screening": arXiv:2009.05418
- "The synthesis of Hibbert ketone structures in technical lignins": Org. Biomol. Chem., 2016, 14, 10023 10030